A Guide to the Frederick W. Knipe papers FA029
Rockefeller Archive Center
Frederick W. Knipe collection
1930-1951
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
Knipe, Frederick W.
FA029
15 Cubic Feet 17 reels of film and photographs. 15 cubic feet is just a placeholder until extent can be determined.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for scholarly research without restriction.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
File Plan
Former Classification: IV 2A 17
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Frederick W. Knipe deposited his collection with the Rockefeller Foundation Archives in June 1969.
Scope and Contents
Important subjects in this collection include: malaria control, drainage of mosquito breeding, development and use of spraying equipment for insecticides.
Biographical / Historical
Frederick W. Knipe was born in 1893 in Hughesville, Pennsylvania. Attending Penn State from 1913-1917 and Iowa State College from 1919-1920, he studied agricultural engineering and secured a license as a drainage and irrigation engineer. From 1920-1930, Mr. Knipe was Assistant Professor of Engineering at Connecticut Agricultural College and Consulting Engineer for the Raymond Keeler Contracting Company.
Joining the International Health Division in 1930, Mr. Knipe took part in the Rockefeller Foundation's anti-malaria campaigns. From 1930-1937, he worked in Bulgaria and Albania. Transferred to Madras State, India in 1937, he participated in the first area-wide campaigns using insecticide effectively against the adult female mosquito. He remained in India until 1942, when he was attached to the U. S. Army malaria control project in Florida. In Rome in 1944, he served as advisor on malaria control for the Army of Occupation; he then joined the Sardinian Project in 1946. Mr. Knipe was assigned to the Malaria Institute of India in 1952, where he taught the use of equipment for malaria control. He retired from the Rockefeller Foundation in 1958.
A major professional interest of Mr. Knipe's had always been an efficient and effective sprayer for the insecticide. While in Italy he designed and built sprayers and then in India worked on perfecting a portable sprayer. There they made their own equipment to manufacture the insecticide, made their own sprayers, and assembled their own power equipment to activate the sprayers.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement
Arranged in 2 series:
Series 1021: Photographs.
Series 2: Audiovisual materials.
Insecticides; DDT (Insecticide); Technology; Public health; Malaria; Rockefeller Foundation; Knipe, Frederick W.; Rockefeller Foundation; Knipe, Frederick W.
- Photographs, 1021
  File Plan
  P/1021
  - Durazzo Lagoon Salinification, Albania (Box 7, Folder 67)
    Scope and Contents
    Lagoons, canals, construction.
  - Durazzo Lagoon Salinification, Albania (Box 7, Folder 68)
    Lagoons, bridges, construction, canals.
  - Tirana River Project, Albania (Box 7, Folder 69)
    Canals, irrigation, agriculture, dams, construction.
- Audiovisual materials, 2
  Biographical / Historical
  Frederick Knipe was a staff member of the International Health Division of the Rockefeller Foundation.
  Arrangement
  Alphabetically.
  The RAC has several silent films from the 1930s about the Tirana River Project in Albania and the efforts to combat malaria throughout the Balkans and in India.
  Conditions Governing Access
  When requesting to view films -- please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1902).
  If the item does not have a designated AV number, please refer to the Title and the Film Number (which consists of a combination of Roman numerals and alphanumerics - example: III 14.1-6).
  - Albania: Durazzo, Tirana, 1930-1937 (Reel AV 806)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    All inquires to view films require advanced notice of at least 24 hours, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those not available in modern formats, may be restricted from scholarly access at the discretion of RAC.
    Scope and Contents note
    Footage from malaria efforts in Albania (1930-1937), Durazzo (1930-1932), and Tirana (1933-1935). Scenes of drainage project, salinification of lagoon, killing mosquitoes with salt, Dr. Lewis Hackett, Knipe opening a dike.
    IV 2 A 17 Fb 4
  - Albania: Porto Romano, 1932 (Reel AV 807)
    1932 footage of the lagoon in Porto Romano: automatic tide gates, canal entrance; also the lab and headquarters at Tirana.
    IV 2 A 17 Fb 5
  - Albania: Shokoset, Tirana (Reel AV 808)
    Footage of canal construction and usage
    IV 2 A17 Fb 6
  - Albania: Tirana Part I (Reel AV 809)
    Tirana River Project: footage of Isuurush Canal and Siphon Dam on the Llana River
    IV 2 A17 Fb 7
  - Albania: Tirana Part II (Reel AV 810)
    Tirana River Project: Dr. Russell and Dr. G.K. Strode opening the canal and the Calco irrigation gate, the first in Albania.
    IV 2 A17 Fb 8
  - Albania: Tirana Part III (Reel AV 811)
    Tirana River Project: finishing construction of the dam and scenes of the dam in action during a flood.
    IV 2 A17 Fb 9
  - Bulgaria: Ezernitza Part I (Box 1, Dvd AV 803, Reel AV 803)
    Footage of the countryside, market day, gypsies dancing at Petrich, washing at a hot water spring, a canal; Dr. Ralph Collins measuring water.
    Existence and Location of Copies note
    Two copies of access DVD.
    IV 2 A17 Fb 1
  - Bulgaria: Ezernitza Part II, 1930 (Box 1, Dvd AV 804, Reel AV 804)
    1930 Footage of the main canal being inspected by Knipe and Dr. G.K. Strode
    IV 2 A17 Fb 2
  - Bulgaria: Ezernitza Part III (Box 1, Dvd AV 805, Reel AV 805)
    Scenes in Luka and Topolnitza: irrigating for corn, building dams, sickling hay
    IV 2 A17 Fb 3
  - India: Madras Part I (Reel AV 817, Box 1, Dvd AV 817)
    Footage of canal construction in Madras State (now Tamil Nadu): mixing plaster by foot, removing earth and stumps; dedication of the Pattukkottai scheme by Dr. Rojan.
    IV 2 A17 Fb 15
  - India: Madras Part II (Reel AV 818, Box 1, Dvd AV 818)
    Footage of efforts to kill mosquitoes; pyrethrum spray gun, spraying village houses and rice nurseries.
    IV 2 A17 Fb 16
  - India: Madras Part III (Reel AV 820, Box 1, Dvd AV 820)
    Typical scene of mosquito treatments; footage of Sukkur Barrage, largest in India.
    IV 2 A17 Fb 17
  - Malaria War Areas, 1942-1944 (Reel AV 816)
    1942-1944 officer training film from World War II: draining mosquito breeding areas, ditch blasting, stumpage,
    IV 2 A17 Fb 14
  - Sardinia, 1930-1932 (Reel AV 813)
    Only available on originial 16 mm film.
    1930-1932 footage from tour of Sardinia for group, including Dr. Rollo Hill, Lewis Hackett, Dr. Wilson G. Smillie, and Fred Knipe. Siniscola tour, IHD conference, visit to Sorrento, Italy. Also includes Dr. F.F. Russell, Dr. Rollo Hill, Dr. Marshall Balfour, Dr. Ralph Collins, Dr. Elizabeth Crowell, and engineer Dan Wright.
    IV 2 A17 Fb 11
  - Sardinia: Erlass Project Part I (Reel AV 812)
    Introduction to Sardinia: footage of villages, coastline, aqueduct ceremony, water wheel powered by a donkey, local life.
    IV 2 A17 Fb 10
  - Sardinia: Erlass Project Part II (Reel AV 814)
    Footage of the Oliena district, explosives used on drainage projects, clearing riverbeds, curing tobacco, construction on canals.
    IV 2 A17 Fb 12
  - Sardinia Erlass Part III (Reel AV 815)
    Footage of efforts against malaria: insecticide development in factories, spraying with helicopters, burning dry vegetation to reveal breeding areas
    IV 2 A17 Fb 13